I would like to talk today
أود أن أتحدث اليوم
about what I think is one of the greatest adventures
حول ما أعتقد أنها إحدى أعظم المغامرات
human beings have embarked upon,
التي شرع البشر فيها،
which is the quest to understand the universe
وهي السعي نحو فهم الكون
and our place in it.
ومكاننا فيه.
My own interest in this subject, and my passion for it,
اهتمامي الخاص بهذا الموضوع، وشغفي به،
began rather accidentally.
بدأ في الواقع صدفة.
I had bought a copy of this book,
كنت قد اشتريت نسخة من هذا الكتاب ،
"The Universe and Dr. Einstein" --
"الكون و... د. أينشتاين" --
a used paperback from a secondhand bookstore in Seattle.
كتاب ورقي الغلاف من محل كتب مستعملة في سياتل.
A few years after that, in Bangalore,
بعد ذلك سنوات قليلة، في بانغلور،
I was finding it hard to fall asleep one night,
كنت أجد صعوبة في النوم في إحدى الليالي،
and I picked up this book,
فالتقطت هذا الكتاب،
thinking it would put me to sleep in 10 minutes.
معتقدا أنه سيجعلني أنام في غضون 10 دقائق.
And as it happened,
وكما حدث،
I read it from midnight to five in the morning in one shot.
قرأته من منتصف الليل حتى الخامسة صباحا دفعة واحدة.
And I was left with this intense feeling
ولقد تركني بشعور مكثف
of awe and exhilaration
من الرهبة والبهجة
at the universe
من الكون
and our own ability to understand as much as we do.
وقدرتنا على الفهم بقدر ما نفعل.
And that feeling hasn't left me yet.
وهذا الشعور لم يفارقني حتى الان.
That feeling was the trigger for me
هذا الشعور كان بمثابة حافز
to actually change my career --
جعلني في الواقع أغير مسيرتي--
from being a software engineer to become a science writer --
من مهندس برمجيات إلى كاتب علوم --
so that I could partake in the joy of science,
حتى أستطيع المشاركة في فرحة للعلوم ،
and also the joy of communicating it to others.
وفرحة ابلاغها للآخرين كذلك.
And that feeling also led me
وهذا الشعور أيضا قادني
to a pilgrimage of sorts,
إلى نوع من الحج،
to go literally to the ends of the earth
للذهاب حرفيا إلى أقاصي الأرض
to see telescopes, detectors,
لرؤية التلسكوبات، والكاشفات،
instruments that people are building, or have built,
آلات يبنيها الناس، أو قد بنوها،
in order to probe the cosmos
من أجل استكشاف الكون
in greater and greater detail.
بتفصيل أكبر وأكبر.
So it took me from places like Chile --
وقد أخذتني الرحلة إلى أماكن مثل تشيلي --
the Atacama Desert in Chile --
صحراء اتاكاما في تشيلي --
to Siberia,
إلى سيبيريا ،
to underground mines
إلى مناجم تحت الأرض،
in the Japanese Alps, in Northern America,
في جبال الألب اليابانية، وفي أمريكا الشمالية،
all the way to Antarctica
على طول الطريق الى القارة القطبية الجنوبية
and even to the South Pole.
وحتى القطب الجنوبي.
And today I would like to share with you
واليوم أود أن أشارككم
some images, some stories of these trips.
بعض الصور وبعض القصص من هذه الرحلات.
I have been basically spending the last few years
وقد قضيت السنوات القليلة الماضية أساسا
documenting the efforts
في توثيق جهود
of some extremely intrepid men and women
رجال ونساء غاية في الإقدام
who are putting,
الذين يضعون ،
literally at times, their lives at stake
أحيانا حرفيا، حياتهم على المحك
working in some very remote and very hostile places
بالعمل في بعض الأماكن النائية جدا وغاية في العدائية
so that they may gather the faintest signals from the cosmos
حتى يتسنى لهم جمع أضعف الاشارات من الكون
in order for us to understand this universe.
ليتسنى لنا أن نفهم هذا الكون.
And I first begin with a pie chart --
وأبدأ أولا مع مخطط دائري.
and I promise this is the only pie chart
وأعدكم أنه المخطط الدائري الوحيد
in the whole presentation --
في العرض كله.
but it sets up the state of our knowledge of the cosmos.
لكنه أساس وضعية معرفتنا للكون.
All the theories in physics that we have today
كل نظريات الفيزياء التي لدينا اليوم
properly explain what is called normal matter --
تشرح بشكل صحيح ما يسمى بالمادة الطبيعية --
the stuff that we're all made of --
الاشياء التي تكوننا جميعا --
and that's four percent of the universe.
وتشكل أربعة في المئة من الكون.
Astronomers and cosmologists and physicists think
علماء الفلك وعلماء الكونيات والفيزيائيون يعتقدون
that there is something called dark matter in the universe,
أن هناك شيء يسمى المادة المظلمة في الكون،
which makes up 23 percent of the universe,
التي تشكل 23 في المئة من الكون ،
and something called dark energy,
وشيء يدعى الطاقة المظلمة،
which permeates the fabric of space-time,
الذي تتخلل نسيج الزمكان ،
that makes up another 73 percent.
ما يشكل 73 أخرى في المئة.
So if you look at this pie chart, 96 percent of the universe,
وبالتالي إذا نظرتم الى هذا الرسم البياني، 96 في المئة من الكون،
at this point in our exploration of it,
في هذه المرحلة من استكشافنا له،
is unknown or not well understood.
غير معروفة أو غير مفهومة جيدا.
And most of the experiments, telescopes that I went to see
ومعظم التجارب ، والتلسكوبات التي ذهبت لرؤيتها
are in some way addressing this question,
تعالج نوعا ما هذا السؤال،
these two twin mysteries of dark matter and dark energy.
هذين التوأمين الغامضين من الطاقة والمادة المظلمتين.
I will take you first to an underground mine
سآخذك أولا إلى منجم تحت الارض
in Northern Minnesota
في شمال ولاية مينيسوتا
where people are looking
حيث يبحث الناس
for something called dark matter.
عن شيء يسمى المادة المظلمة.
And the idea here is that they are looking for a sign
والفكرة هنا هي أنهم يبحثون عن إشارة
of a dark matter particle hitting one of their detectors.
من جسيمات المادة المظلمة تضرب واحد من أجهزة الكشف.
And the reason why they have to go underground
والسبب الذي دعاهم للذهاب تحت الارض
is that, if you did this experiment on the surface of the Earth,
هو أنه ، إن قمت بهاته التجربة على سطح الأرض،
the same experiment would be swamped by signals
نفس التجربة ستكون مغمورة بإشارات
that could be created by things like cosmic rays,
قد تسببها أشياء مثل الأشعة الكونية،
ambient radio activity,
النشاط الإشعاعي المحيط،
even our own bodies. You might not believe it,
وحتى أجسامنا. قد لا تصدقون ذلك،
but even our own bodies are radioactive enough to disturb this experiment.
ولكن حتى أجسامنا تكون مشعة بما يكفي للتشويش على هذه التجربة.
So they go deep inside mines
وبالتالي يذهبون عميقا داخل المناجم
to find a kind of environmental silence
لإيجاد نوع من الصمت البيئي
that will allow them to hear
الذي سيسمح لهم بالاستماع
the ping of a dark matter particle hitting their detector.
رنين جسيمات المادة المظلمة وهي تضرب أجهزة الكشف.
And I went to see one of these experiments,
وذهبت لرؤية إحدى هذه التجارب ،
and this is actually -- you can barely see it,
وهذا هو في الواقع -- تستطيع بالكاد رؤيتها،
and the reason for that is it's entirely dark in there --
والسبب في ذلك هو ان المكان مظلم تماما هناك.
this is a cavern that was left behind by the miners
هذا هو الكهف الذي تركه عمال المناجم
who left this mine in 1960.
الذين تركوا هذه المناجم في 1960.
And physicists came and started using it
وجاء علماء الفيزياء وبدؤوا في استخدامه
sometime in the 1980s.
في وقت ما في الثمانينيات.
And the miners in the early part of the last century
وعمال المنجم في أوائل القرن الماضي
worked, literally, in candlelight.
كانوا يعملون، بضوء الشموع، حرفيا.
And today, you would see this inside the mine,
واليوم ، سترون هذا داخل المنجم،
half a mile underground.
نصف ميل تحت الارض.
This is one of the largest underground labs in the world.
هذا هو واحد من أكبر المختبرات التحت أرضية في العالم.
And, among other things, they're looking for dark matter.
ومن بين أمور أخرى، يبحثون عن المادة المظلمة.
There is another way to search for dark matter,
هناك طريقة أخرى للبحث عن المادة المظلمة،
which is indirectly.
وهي غير مباشرة.
If dark matter exists in our universe,
إذا كانت المادة المظلمة موجودة في عالمنا،
in our galaxy,
في مجرتنا،
then these particles should be smashing together
ثم ينبغي أن تحطم هذه الجزيئات معا
and producing other particles that we know about --
وتنتج الجزيئات الأخرى التي نعرفها --
one of them being neutrinos.
واحد منها هي النيوترونات.
And neutrinos you can detect
ويمكنك الكشف عن النيوترونات
by the signature they leave
من خلال التوقيع الذي تتركه
when they hit water molecules.
حين تضرب جزيئات الماء.
When a neutrino hits a water molecule
عندما يضرب نيوترينو جزيئة الماء
it emits a kind of blue light,
ينبعث منه نوع من الضوء الأزرق،
a flash of blue light,
ومضة من الضوء الأزرق،
and by looking for this blue light,
وبالبحث عن هذا الضوء الأزرق،
you can essentially understand something about the neutrino
يمكنك أساسا فهم شيء عن النيوترينو
and then, indirectly, something about the dark matter
ثم، وبشكل غير مباشر، أمر حول المادة المظلمة
that might have created this neutrino.
التي قد تكون أنشأت هذا النيوترينو.
But you need very, very large volumes of water
ولكنكم في حاجة إلى أحجام كبيرة جدا من المياه
in order to do this.
ولكي نفعل هذا.
You need something like tens of megatons of water --
كنت بحاجة الى ما يقارب عشرات الميغا أطنان من الماء --
almost a gigaton of water --
تقريبا غيغاطن من الماء --
in order to have any chance of catching this neutrino.
من أجل أدنى فرصة لالتقاط هذا النيوترينو.
And where in the world would you find such water?
وأين قد تجد تلك المياه في العالم؟
Well the Russians have a tank in their own backyard.
حسنا الروس لديهم خزان في فنائهم الخلفي.
This is Lake Baikal.
هذه بحيرة بايكال.
It is the largest lake in the world. It's 800 km long.
وهي أكبر بحيرة في العالم. بطول 800 كم.
It's about 40 to 50 km wide
حوالي 40 إلى 50 كلم كعرض
in most places,
في معظم الأماكن،
and one to two kilometers deep.
وما بين 1-2 كلم في العمق.
And what the Russians are doing
وما يفعله الروس
is they're building these detectors
هو انهم يبنون أجهزة كشف
and immersing them about a kilometer beneath the surface of the lake
ويغمرونها بحوالي كيلومتر تحت سطح البحيرة
so that they can watch for these flashes of blue light.
حتى يتمكنوا من مراقبة ومضات من الضوء الأزرق.
And this is the scene that greeted me when I landed there.
وهذا هو المشهد الذي صادفته عندما هبطت هناك.
This is Lake Baikal
هذه بحيرة بايكال
in the peak of the Siberian winter.
في ذروة فصل الشتاء في سيبيريا.
The lake is entirely frozen.
هذه البحيرة متجمدة كليا.
And the line of black dots
وخط النقاط السوداء
that you see in the background,
التي ترون في الخلفية،
that's the ice camp where the physicists are working.
هذا هو مخيم الجليد حيث يعمل الفيزيائيون.
The reason why they have to work in winter
السبب الذي جعلهم يعملون في فصل الشتاء
is because they don't have the money to work in summer and spring,
هو أنهم لا يملكون ما يكفي من المال للعمل في الصيف والربيع،
which, if they did that,
بحيث، إن فعلوا ذلك،
they would need ships and submersibles to do their work.
فإنهم سيحتاجون سفنا وغواصات للقيام بعملهم.
So they wait until winter --
ثم ينتظرون حتى فصل الشتاء --
the lake is completely frozen over --
البحيرة تتجمد تماما --
and they use this meter-thick ice
ويستخدمون هذا الجليد والذي يبلغ سمكه مترا
as a platform on which to establish their ice camp and do their work.
كمنصة لإقامة معسكرهم الجليدي والقيام بعملهم.
So this is the Russians working on the ice
وهكذا هؤلاء هم الروس يعملون على الجليد
in the peak of the Siberian winter.
في ذروة فصل الشتاء في سيبيريا.
They have to drill holes in the ice,
عليهم حفر ثقوب في الجليد،
dive down into the water -- cold, cold water --
الغوص في المياه -- الباردة ، المياه الباردة --
to get hold of the instrument, bring it up,
لالتقاط الجهاز، ورفعه نحو السطح،
do any repairs and maintenance that they need to do,
القيام بأي عمليات إصلاح وصيانة يتعين عليهم القيام بها،
put it back and get out before the ice melts.
إعادته ثم الخروج قبل ان يذوب الجليد.
Because that phase of solid ice lasts for two months
لأن مرحلة الجليد الصلب تلك تستمر لمدة شهرين
and it's full of cracks.
ويكون مليئا بالشقوق.
And you have to imagine, there's an entire sea-like lake
وعليكم أن تتخيلوا، أن هناك بحيرة تشبه البحر بأكملها
underneath, moving.
تحتها ، تتحرك.
I still don't understand this one Russian man
ما زلت لا أفهم هذا الرجل الروسي
working in his bare chest,
يشتغل بصدر عار،
but that tells you how hard he was working.
لكن ذلك يخبركم كيف كان يعمل بجد.
And these people, a handful of people,
وهؤلاء الناس، حفنة من الناس،
have been working for 20 years,
كانوا يشتغلون لعشرين سنة،
looking for particles that may or may not exist.
باحثين عن جزيئات قد توجد أو قد لا توجد.
And they have dedicated their lives to it.
وقد كرسوا حياتهم لذلك.
And just to give you an idea,
وفقط لإعطائكم فكرة،
they have spent 20 million over 20 years.
قد صرف هؤلاء 20 مليون دولار على مدى 20 عاما.
It's very harsh conditions.
انها ظروف قاسية جدا.
They work on a shoestring budget.
ويعملون بميزانية ضئيلة.
The toilets there are literally holes in the ground
المراحيض هناك هي حرفيا عبارة عن ثقوب في الأرض
covered with a wooden shack.
مغطاة بكوخ خشبي.
And it's that basic,
الأمر بتلك البساطة،
but they do this every year.
لكنهم يقومون بذلك كل عام.
From Siberia to the Atacama Desert in Chile,
ومن سيبيريا الى صحراء أتاكاما في شيلي،
to see something called The Very Large Telescope.
لنرى ما يسمى بالتلسكوب الكبير جدا.
The Very Large Telescope
التلسكوب الكبير جدا
is one of these things that astronomers do --
هو واحدة من هذه الأشياء التي يسميها الفلكيين --
they name their telescopes rather unimaginatively.
يسمون تلسكوباتهم بالا خيال.
I can tell you for a fact,
استطيع ان أؤكد لكم أنهم،
that the next one that they're planning is called The Extremely Large Telescope.
يخططون لتسمية التلسكوب القادم بالتلسكوب الكبير للغاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you wouldn't believe it,
لن تصدقوا ذلك،
but the one after that is going to be called The Overwhelmingly Large Telescope.
ولكن الذي بعده سيسمى بالتلسكوب الهائل الضخامة.
But nonetheless,
لكن على الرغم من ذلك،
it's an extraordinary piece of engineering.
انها قطعة هندسية مذهلة.
These are four 8.2 meter telescopes.
هذه أربع تلسكوبات بعلو 8.2 متر.
And these telescopes, among other things,
وهذه التلسكوبات ، من بين أمور أخرى،
they're being used to study
يتم استخدامها لدراسة
how the expansion of the universe is changing with time.
كيفية يتغير توسع الكون بمرور الوقت.
And the more you understand that,
وبقدر ما تفهم ذلك،
the better you would understand
بقدر ما تفهم
what this dark energy that the universe is made of is all about.
ماهية الطاقة المظلمة -- التي تشكل الكون --
And one piece of engineering that I want to leave you with
والقطعة الهندسية الذي أود أن أترككم معها
as regards this telescope
فيما يتعلق بهذا التلسكوب
is the mirror.
هي المرآة.
Each mirror, there are four of them,
كل مرآة، وهناك أربعة منها،
is made of a single piece of glass,
مصنوعة من قطعة واحدة من الزجاج،
a monolithic piece of high-tech ceramic,
قطعة متجانسة من السيراميك ذي التكنولوجيا العالية،
that has been ground down and polished to such accuracy
التي تم تمسيده وصقله لدقة
that the only way to understand what that is
إلى درجة أن السبيل لفهمه ذلك هو
is [to] imagine a city like Paris,
هو تصور مدينة مثل باريس،
with all its buildings and the Eiffel Tower,
مع كل مبانيها وبرج ايفل،
if you grind down Paris to that kind of accuracy,
ومن ثم تسوية باريس بهذه الدقة،
you would be left with bumps that are one millimeter high.
سوف نجد مطبات بعلو مليمتر واحد.
And that's the kind of polishing that these mirrors have endured.
وهذا هو التلميع التي تعرضت له هذه المرايا.
An extraordinary set of telescopes.
مجموعة غير عادية من التلسكوبات.
Here's another view of the same.
وهنا مشهد آخر لها.
The reason why you have to build these telescopes
السبب الذي جعلنا نبني هذه التلسكوبات
in places like the Atacama Desert
في أماكن مثل صحراء أتاكاما
is because of the high altitude desert.
هو بسبب علو ارتفاع الصحراء.
The dry air is really good for telescopes,
والهواء الجاف مناسب جدا للتلسكوبات،
and also, the cloud cover is below the summit of these mountains
وكذلك، غطاء السحب هو أدنى من قمة هذا الجبل
so that the telescopes have
بحيث يكون للتلسكوبات
about 300 days of clear skies.
حوالي 300 يوما من السماء الصافية.
Finally, I want to take you to Antarctica.
وأخيرا، أريد أخذكم إلى القارة القطبية الجنوبية.
I want to spend most of my time on this part of the world.
أريد أن أقضي معظم وقتي في هذا الجزء من العالم.
This is cosmology's final frontier.
هذه هي الحد الأقصى لعلم الكونيات.
Some of the most amazing experiments,
بعض من التجارب المدهشة ،
some of the most extreme experiments,
تجارب أكثر تطرفا،
are being done in Antarctica.
تجرى في القارة القطبية الجنوبية.
I was there to view something called a long-duration balloon flight,
كنت هناك لعرض ما يسمى الرحلة-الطويلة للبالون،
which basically takes telescopes and instruments
الذي يأخذ أساسا التلسكوبات والتجهيزات
all the way to the upper atmosphere,
إلى أعالي الغلاف الجوي،
the upper stratosphere, 40 km up.
الطبقة العليا من الستراتوسفير، بعلو 40 كم.
And that's where they do their experiments,
وهناك يجرون تجاربهم،
and then the balloon, the payload, is brought down.
ومن ثم يتم سحب البالون والحمولة، إلى الأسفل.
So this is us landing on the Ross Ice Shelf in Antarctica.
هذا نحن لحظة الهبوط على الجرف الجليدي روس في القارة القطبية الجنوبية.
That's an American C-17 cargo plane
تلك طائرة شحن أمريكية من نوع C-17
that flew us from New Zealand
طارت بنا من نيوزيلندا
to McMurdo in Antarctica.
إلى ماكموردو في القطب الجنوبي.
And here we are about to board our bus.
وهنا نحن بصدد ركوب حافلتنا.
And I don't know if you can read the lettering,
ولا أعرف إن كان بإمكانكم قراءة المنقوش،
but it says, "Ivan the Terribus."
لكنه يقول "إيفان التيريبوس".
And that's taking us to McMurdo.
وقد أخذنا إلى ماكموردو.
And this is the scene that greets you in McMurdo.
وهذا هو المشهد الذي في الإستقبال في ماكموردو.
And you barely might be able to make out
وتستطيع بالكاد تمييز
this hut here.
هذا الكوخ هنا.
This hut was built by Robert Falcon Scott and his men
قد بني هذا الكوخ من طرف روبرت فالكون سكوت ورجاله
when they first came to Antarctica
عندما جاؤوا اولا الى القارة القطبية الجنوبية
on their first expedition to go to the South Pole.
في رحلتهم الأولى إلى القطب الجنوبي.
Because it's so cold,
لأنه بارد جدا،
the entire contents of that hut is still as they left it,
محتويات هذا الكوخ لا تزال كما تركوها،
with the remnants of the last meal they cooked still there.
مع بقايا آخر وجبة طبخوها هناك
It's an extraordinary place.
انه مكان غير عادي.
This is McMurdo itself. About a thousand people work here in summer,
هذه ماكموردو نفسها. حوالي ألف شخص يعملون هنا في الصيف،
and about 200 in winter
وحوالي 200 في فصل الشتاء
when it's completely dark for six months.
عندما تكون مظلمة تماما طيلة ستة أشهر.
I was here to see the launch
كنت هنا لرؤية اطلاق
of this particular type of instrument.
هذا النوع بعينه من التجهيزات.
This is a cosmic ray experiment
هذه تجربة أشعة كونية
that has been launched all the way to the upper-stratosphere
والتي تم إطلاقها على طول الطريق إلى الستراتوسفير العلوي
to an altitude of 40 km.
الى علو 40 كيلومترا.
What I want you to imagine is this is two tons in weight.
ما أريدكم أن تتخيلوه هو أطنان من الوزن.
So you're using a balloon
لذلك يستخدم بالون
to carry something that is two tons
لرفع ما يساوي طنين
all the way to an altitude of 40 km.
على طول الطريق الى ارتفاع 40 كيلومترا.
And the engineers, the technicians, the physicists
والمهندسون والفنيون والفيزيائيون
have all got to assemble on the Ross Ice Shelf,
عليهم جميعا التجمع على الجرف الجليدي روس،
because Antarctica -- I won't go into the reasons why --
لأن القارة القطبية الجنوبية -- وأنا لن أخوض في الأسباب --
but it's one of the most favorable places for doing these balloon launches,
لكنه واحد من أكثر الأماكن الملائمة لإطلاق هذه البالونات،
except for the weather.
فيما عدا الاحوال الجوية.
The weather, as you can imagine,
الطقس، كما قد تتخيلون،
this is summer, and you're standing on 200 ft of ice.
هذا الصيف ، وكنت واقفا على 200 قدم من الجليد.
And there's a volcano behind,
وهناك بركان في الخلف،
which has glaciers at the very top.
بأنهار جليدية على القمة.
And what they have to do
وما يتعين عليهم القيام به
is they have to assemble the entire balloon --
هو تجميع البالون بالكامل --
the fabric, parachute and everything -- on the ice
النسيج والمظلة وكل شيء -- على الجليد
and then fill it up with helium.
ونفخه بعد ذلك بالهيليوم.
And that process takes about two hours.
وهذه العملية تستغرق حوالي الساعتين.
And the weather can change as they're putting together this whole assembly.
ويمكن أن يتغير الطقس وهم يجمعون التشكيلة بأكملها.
For instance, here they are laying down the balloon fabric behind,
على سبيل المثال، ها هم قد وضعوا نسيج البالون في الخلف،
which is eventually going to be filled up with helium.
والذي سيتم في نهاية المطاف نفخه بالهليوم.
Those two trucks you see at the very end
تلك الشاحنتان التي ترون في النهاية البعيدة
carry 12 tanks each of compressed helium.
تحمل 12 خزانا من الهيليوم المضغوط.
Now, in case the weather changes before the launch,
الآن، في حالة تغير الطقس قبل الاطلاق،
they have to actually pack everything back up into their boxes
عليهم حزم كل شيء مرة أخرى وإعادته إلى الصناديق
and take it out back to McMurdo Station.
وإخراجه مرة أخرى إلى محطة ماكموردو.
And this particular balloon,
وهذا البالون بذاته،
because it has to launch two tons of weight,
لأن عليه حمل طنين من الوزن،
is an extremely huge balloon.
هو بالون بالغ الضخامة.
The fabric alone weighs two tons.
النسيج لوحده يزن طنين.
In order to minimize the weight,
ومن أجل تقليل الوزن،
it's very thin, it's as thin as a sandwich wrapper.
جعلوه رقيق جدا، انها رقيقة مثل غلاف شطيرة.
And if they have to pack it back,
وإذا كان عليهم حزمه مجددا،
they have to put it into boxes
عليهم وضعه في صناديق
and stamp on it so that it fits into the box again --
والضغط عليها بحيث تلائم الصندوق مرة أخرى --
except, when they did it first,
باستثناء أنه، عندما فعلوا ذلك في المرة الأولى،
it would have been done in Texas.
قاموا به في ولاية تكساس.
Here, they can't do it with the kind shoes they're wearing,
وهنا، لا يمكنهم أن يفعلوا ذلك بنوع الأحذية الذي يرتدونه،
so they have to take their shoes off,
لذلك يتوجب عليهم خلع أخذيتهم،
get barefoot into the boxes, in this cold,
أن يكونوا حافي القدمين في الصناديق في هذا البرد
and do that kind of work.
وأداء ذلك النوع من العمل.
That's the kind of dedication these people have.
وتلك هي درجة التفاني لدى هؤلاء الناس.
Here's the balloon being filled up with helium,
وهنا البالون يتم نفخه بالهيليوم،
and you can see it's a gorgeous sight.
ويمكنك ان تروا أنه مشهد رائع.
Here's a scene
هنا مقطع
that shows you the balloon and the payload end-to-end.
يعرض البالون وحمولة في النهاية.
So the balloon is being filled up with helium on the left-hand side,
بحيث يتم ملء البالون بالهيليوم على الجانب الأيمن،
and the fabric actually runs all the way to the middle
والنسيج يستمر فعلا على طول الطريق إلى الوسط
where there's a piece of electronics and explosives
حيث هناك قطعة من الالكترونيات والمتفجرات
being connected to a parachute,
متصلة بالمظلة،
and then the parachute is then connected to the payload.
ومن ثم يتم توصيل المظلة بالحمولة.
And remember, all this wiring is being done
وتذكروا، أن ربط كل هذه الأسلاك يتم
by people in extreme cold, in sub-zero temperatures.
من طرف أناس في البرد القارس، في درجات حرارة دون الصفر.
They're wearing about 15 kg of clothing and stuff,
يرتدون نحو 15 كلغ من الملابس والاشياء،
but they have to take their gloves off in order to do that.
ولكن عليهم نزع قفازاتهم للقيام بذلك.
And I would like to share with you a launch.
وأود أن أشارككم الاطلاق.
(Video) Radio: Okay, release the balloon,
(فيديو) راديو: حسنا، أطلقوا البالون،
release the balloon, release the balloon.
أطلقوا البالون، أطلقوا البالون.
Anil Ananthaswamy: And I'll finally like to leave you with two images.
أنيل أنانثاسوامي: وأود أن أترككم أخيرا مع صورتين.
This is an observatory in the Himalayas, in Ladakh in India.
هذا مرصد في جبال الهيمالايا، في لاداخ في الهند.
And the thing I want you to look at here
وما أريد منكم أن تننظروا إليه هنا
is the telescope on the right-hand side.
هو تلسكوب في الجانب الأيمن.
And on the far left there
وعلى أقصى اليسار هناك
is a 400 year-old Buddhist monastery.
هو دير بوذي عمره 400 عاما.
This is a close-up of the Buddhist monastery.
هذه صورة مقربة للدير البوذي.
And I was struck by the juxtaposition
وقد أدهشني تجاور
of these two enormous disciplines that humanity has.
هذين التخصصين العظيمين لدى الإنسانية.
One is exploring the cosmos on the outside,
واحد هو استكشاف الكون الخارجي،
and the other one is exploring our interior being.
والآخر هو استكشاف ذواتنا الداخلية.
And both require silence of some sort.
وكلاهما يتطلب نوعا من الصمت.
And what struck me was
وما أدهشني هو
every place that I went to to see these telescopes,
في كل مكان ذهبت إليه لرؤية هذه التلسكوبات،
the astronomers and cosmologists
علماء الفلك وعلماء الكون
are in search of a certain kind of silence,
في بحث عن نوع معين من الصمت،
whether it's silence from radio pollution
سواء كان ذلك الصمت من التلوث بموجات الراديو
or light pollution or whatever.
أو التلوث الضوئي أو أيا كان.
And it was very obvious
وكان واضحا جدا
that, if we destroy these silent places on Earth,
أنه، إن دمرنا هذه الأماكن الصامتة على الأرض،
we will be stuck on a planet without the ability to look outwards,
سوف نكون عالقين على كوكب من دون القدرة على النظر إلى الخارج ،
because we will not be able to understand the signals that come from outer space.
لأننا لن نكون قادرين على فهم الاشارات التي تأتي من الفضاء الخارجي.
Thank you.
شكرا لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)